Guide to the Gregory Corso Papers, 1960-1970
Department of Special Collections
Gregory Corso Papers,
1960-1970
Special Collections M721
Purchased, 1994, as part of the Stephen Rodefer papers.
1 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Purchased, 1994, as part of the Stephen Rodefer papers. Corso had given these materials to Rodefer in payment for a large telephone bill Corso had accrued when he stayed with Rodefer in Corrales, New Mexico, in 1969.
ABSTRACT
The material in the collection is somewhat fragmentary; many of the manuscript pages are handwritten and unidentifiable as part of larger works, although the emendations on the drafts provide a glimpse of Corso's revision process. The correspondence includes both professional and highly personal material.
BIOGRAPHY
Gregory Nunzio Corso, an associate of Beat writers Jack Kerouac, Allen Ginsberg, and Lawrence Ferlinghetti, is the author of over twenty volumes of poetry, numerous magazine articles and essays, plays, and a 1961 novel, The American Express.
Born in New York City in 1930, Corso worked as a migrant laborer, newspaper reporter for the L.A. Examiner, and merchant seaman before joining the English Department at SUNY Buffalo in 1965. In the mid-1950s he began to give public readings of his poetry, often sharing the stage with other Beats. His 1958 volume, Gasoline, marks the beginning of his long association with San Francisco's City Lights Bookstore and the Bay Area in general, which figures prominently in much of Corso's work.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The Gregory Corso Archive includes manuscript notebooks, published materials and personal and professional ephemera of Gregory Corso. They are housed in 3 document boxes and occupy 1.5 linear feet.
The collection covers Corso's work in the 1980s and early 1990s, including both manuscript notebooks and published works. The ephemera includes professional and personal correspondence with Allen Ginsberg as well as materials documenting Corso's public appearances and professional collaborations. The ephemera series also includes photographs of Corso. Most of the items in the collection are signed.
The Corso Papers were received by the Stanford Library as part of the Stephen Rodefer Collection. Corso gave these materials, which were housed in a suitcase at the time, to Rodefer in payment for a large telephone bill Corso had accrued when he stayed with the poet in Corrales, New Mexico, in 1969. During this visit, Corso guest-lectured in Rodefer's class; Rodefer, in turn, hosted Corso's first reading, in ten years.
The material in the collection is somewhat fragmentary; many of the manuscript pages are handwritten and unidentifiable as part of larger works, although the emendations on the drafts provide a glimpse of Corso's revision process. The correspondence in the collection's second box is a sampling of professional and highly personal material, ranging from solicitations for magazine submissions to contract copies, to angry drafts. As representation of Corso's personal and professional life--quite literally what he was carrying around with him--the papers chronicle the important events of Corso's written life in the years 1969-70 and indicate the peripatetic nature of that existence.
CONTAINER LIST
- "All Hallows' Eve in Cleveland" n.d. (TMs and AMs) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Ama Fleming Introduction n.d. (AMs and TMs) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "American Historia Politica" 1970 (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "The American Way" c. 1960s (TMs) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "August Thoughts" 1969 (AMsS) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "The Birth of Earth" n.d. (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Common Sensitivity" n.d. (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "the dancing boy of the spilling air" n.d. (TMs) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Dear Indian" Dec., 1969 (TMs with AN) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Down By the Vacant Lot" n.d. (TMs with AN) (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Elegiac Feelings American" (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Experiences of imagination, dream..." n.d. (TMs with AN) (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "JFK" n.d. (TMs reprint) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "The Hounds of Psychosis" n.d. (TMs) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "Indomitable Moods" n.d. (TMs reprint) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "In this my Pons Asinorum..." n.d. (TMs with AN) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "The Last Poem" n.d. (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "Like I would never kill" n.d. (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "Marriage Ceremony for Hells Angel Wedding" (AmsS) (Box 1, Folder 19)
- "1970 Inventory Assessments" c. 1969-70 (TMs) (Box 1, Folder 20)
- "Old Man Carrying Straw" n.d. (TMsS) (Box 1, Folder 21)
- "Poem for Belle..." January, 1970 (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "St. God...a mystery poem" n.d. (TMs) (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "Ten Poems a Time..." n.d. (TMs with AN) (Box 1, Folder 24)
- "Theme for Bill: the Etymological" n.d. (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "Theme of There's Yet Time" n.d. (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "A 13 Year Old's Visit to Hell" n.d. (TMsS with AN) (Box 1, Folder 27)
- "Thor" n.d. (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 28)
- "3 Days After Stonehenge" n.d.(AMs) (Box 1, Folder 29)
- "What Comes from the Head Automaticly" n.d. (TMs) (Box 1, Folder 30)
- "When Your Child Has Gone to War" n.d. (TMs) (Box 1, Folder 31)
- "Who is the Face in the Mirror..." n.d. (TMsS) (Box 1, Folder 32)
- autobiographical fragments c. 1969-70 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- film project n.d. (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 34)
- draft of a play [?] n.d. (AMs) (Box 1, Folder 35)
- manuscripts--unidentified (Box 1, Folder 36)
- manuscripts--unidentified (Box 1, Folder 37)
- manuscripts--unidentified (Box 1, Folder 38)
- manuscripts--unidentified (Box 1, Folder 39)
- manuscripts--unidentified (Box 1, Folder 40)
- manuscripts--unidentified (Box 1, Folder 41)
- manuscripts--unidentified (Box 1, Folder 42)
- manuscripts--unidentified (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Letters to Corso n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - James F. Botta (poem)
  - Corinth Books, contract copy, SpontaneousRequiem for the American Indian
  - Allen Ginsberg
  - Gotham Book Mart re new material
  - Peter Jones
  - Peter Orlovsky
  - Treasury Department, U.S. Government
  - Wajovi
  - Unsolicited correspondence
- Letters to Corso, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sinclair Beiles
  - City Lights Books, contract Collected Prose [signed by Corso]
  - Doubleday & Co., permission request to reprint "Requiem for 'Bird' Parker"
  - Anthony Huck Finneral
  - Follett Publishing Co., re Chicago 8 defense fund auction
  - Allen Ginsberg
  - Gotham Book Mart
  - Piero Heliczers
  - Harper & Row re complimentary book
  - Patrick King re youth response to Kerouac's death
  - New Directions Publishing Corp. [James Laughlin and Robert McGregor]
  - receipts addressed to Belle Ostrander
- Letters to Corso, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Corinth Books re contracts
  - Caresse Crosby memorial service invitation
  - Fantasy/Galaxy Records re tax forms
  - Lawrence Ferlinghetti
  - Louis Ginsberg
  - Gotham Book Mart
  - Piero Heliczer
  - Midcentury Authors, John Wakeman, ed.
  - New Directions Publishing Corp [James Laughlin]
  - New Directions Publishing Corp. U.S. tax form
  - Phoenix Book Shop
  - Joe Reynolds
  - submission requests
- Drafts of letters by Corso (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Andreas Blaise
  - Belle Carpenter
- Drafts of letters by Corso (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lawrence Ferlinghetti
  - Allen Ginsberg
  - James Laughlin
  - Ted Wilentz
  - to Olga [unidentified] re fame and poverty
  - unidentified fragments
- personal business: writing (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - letter from Donald Allen re NAP royalties
  - royalty statement from Czech government
  - contract copy: "Spontaneous Requiem for theAmerican Indian"
  - tax receipt from City Lights Books, 1969
  - receipts for publishers' advances on Elegiac Feelings American ($500) and Happy Birthday of Death ($200); New Directions Press
  - U.S. census individual report form: 1970
- personal business: miscellaneous receipts (incl. unsigned Prisoner Property Receipt, Santa Fe Jail, Mar. 14, 1970) (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Corso artwork (Box 2, Folder 8)
- printed matter: Andersen's "Takis: Evidence of the Unseen" (Box 2, Folder 9)
- printed matter: manuscripts from others (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Botta (TMs)
  - "anthology of Power" (unknown)
  - "spy poem" (unknown)
  - "the times of the watches" (reprint)
  - education manifesto (reprint)
- printed matter: miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "America Politica Historia..." (reprint from Chelsea Review #8, Oct., 1960
  - Caliche County Rendering Works no. 19
  - "Head Comix"
  - "3 Spare Parts"
  - The New Mexico Review and Legislative Journal, "Who Killed Eulogio Salazar?" 1969
  - "Art: Like the Stumpy Crocus..." NYT Apr. 2, 1966 (review of Raphael Soyer, w/ Ginsberg, diPrima and Corso portrait)
  - miscellaneous fragments
- personal business: artifacts (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - bill for medical treatments Feb. 19-Apr. 1, 1970
  - large envelope containing suitcase debris
- prescription bottle: valium (dated Mar. 3, 1970) (Box 2, Folder 13)